ROBERTO ROBLES

+1 5873307860 | ra.roblesb@gmail.com | www.linkedin.com/in/roberto-roblesb

BUSINESS ANALYST

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Exceedingly thorough Data and Business Analyst with 4 years modifying ongoing business processes to achieve superlative results. Experience gathering and organizing user requirements, managing the procedures and documentation required for software development and implementation, ensuring software quality, and managing the development portfolio. Analyzing data and business processes to make data-driven decisions and reporting results. Solid IT business background in quality control and continuous improvement, as well as professional experience for manufacturing and service companies.

SKILLS

- · Business analysis
- Data analysis and visualization
- Business Process Design
- Reporting skills
- Problem-solver

- MS Office, MS Power BI, Tableau
- MS Visio, Bizagi
- · Python, SQL
- MS Project, JIRA, Balsamiq, Selenium
- AutoCAD, Solidworks, Inventor

WORK HISTORY

BUSINESS ANALYST | 08/2021 to Current PUBLIC WATER COMPANY - EPA EP - Ecuador

- Created a management scorecard for senior management, complete with indicators and management reports.
- Led the team in charge of developing an in-house commercial system from the ground up.
- Improved information delivery to customers by implementing a tool to automate delivery, increasing daily reports sent from 100 to 700.
- Cut the time it took to reconcile client charges from 4 hours to 30 minutes.
- Increased billing users' processing capacity from 50 daily invoices to 300.

PROCESS ENGINEER | 02/2021 to 08/2021 GRUVALCORP S.A. - Ecuador

- Set up the new ERP system, entering 100% of the general production parameters such as costs, process times, waiting times, and so on.
- Conducted a product process study, which reduced shrinkage (waste) from 20-30% to less than 10% on average.
- Developed software to manage raw material inventory control.
- Documented the processes and flows, as well as the improvements that resulted from them.
- Extracted and analyzed data in order to produce reports for senior management.

BUSINESS ANALYST | 02/2018 to 09/2020

REPORNE S.A. - Ecuador

- Enhanced the method for entering commercial clients in the sales area, thereby increasing the global handling capacity of each salesperson by 30%.
- Supervised the integration of the administrative system's data with the accounting system.
- Oversaw a portfolio of technological integrations with service and financial institutions.
- Implemented system optimizations to reduce the average time of technological integrations from 14 to 7 days.
- Responsible of general documentation and the improvement of procedures and processes.
- Guaranteed the quality of the IT department's development by implementing QA tests.
- Developed procedure manuals, instructions, and job profiles by position

EDUCATION

Escuela Superior Politecnica Del Litoral (ESPOL) | Bachelor's Degree in Industrial Engineering Universidad Internacional De La Rioja (UNIR) | MBA

Present

CERTIFICATIONS

- Internal Auditor ISO 9001:2015. Société Générale de Surveillance (SGS). 2017
- Data Analysis and Business Intelligence in Power Bl. ESPOL FIMCP. 2021
- The Business Intelligence Analyst Course. Udemy. 2022
- Business Analysis Certification. Udemy. 2022
- Google Data Analytics Certificate. Coursera Google Career. 2023
- Python for Everybody. Coursera University of Michigan. 2023